<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief narrative of the proceedings of Doctor Parr, and some of the parishioners of Mary Magda'en [sic] - Bermonsey in the county of Surrey against certain people called Quakers, inhabitants of the said parish, for not paying and complying with an illegal tax, laid under pretence of repairing their church ...</title>
            <author>Rawbone, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12354339</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12354339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55863)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1025:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief narrative of the proceedings of Doctor Parr, and some of the parishioners of Mary Magda'en [sic] - Bermonsey in the county of Surrey against certain people called Quakers, inhabitants of the said parish, for not paying and complying with an illegal tax, laid under pretence of repairing their church ...</title>
                  <author>Rawbone, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Joseph Rawbone, Henry Day.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parr, Richard, 1617-1691.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60088:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60088:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF NARRATIVE Of the Proceedings of Doctor Parr, And ſome of the Pariſhioners of <hi>Mary Magdalen-Bermonſey</hi> in the County of SURREY.</p>
            <p>Againſt certain People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> Inhabitants of the ſaid Pariſh, for not Paying and Complying with an Illegal Tax, laid under pretence of Repairing their Church.</p>
            <p>Shewing how ſome of the ſaid people did endeavour (as of right belongeth to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Engliſh man) to defend themſelves from the Rigor and Cruelty of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Courts about the ſame, by ſeeking to gain a Prohibition to ſtop the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the Biſhop's Court, and to bring their Unreaſonble Illegal Impoſition of 1800 <abbr>l.</abbr> upon the ſaid Pariſh to tryal at Common Law; and by what Means they have been prevented therein.</p>
            <p>Alſo an EXHORTORY REPREHENSION upon the whole.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed to prevent a Miſunderſtanding concerning the ſaid people, who are and may be more preſented, as that <hi>they in Enmity, Stubbornneſs and Self-willedneſs have refuſed to pay towards the ſaid Rate, and occaſioned a Charge to the ſaid Pariſh.</hi> Whereas in Truth the Cauſe of their endeavour to defend themſelves was, to keep their Conſciences void of Offence to God and Men (To God, in not yielding to Repair an Idols Temple; for ſo they believe it to be: To Men, in that their Proceeds therein were contrary to all the known Law in being) And having done their endeavour in trying the Courts of Judicature, and finding Iniquity in the place of Judgment, and the Cauſe of the Poor ſleighted, they are clear in their Conſciences, and can leave their Cauſe to God, and lie down in Peace and Good Will to all men. But the gnawing Worm, that never dyes, will faſten upon the Wicked in the Day of Account.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 5.15.</hi>
               </bibl> And moreover I ſaw under the Sun the Place of Judgment, and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity was there; and the Place of Righteouſneſs, and Wickedneſs was there.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60088:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60088:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou mayſt underſtand, we live in a Nation whoſe Laws and conſtituted Government excels moſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the World, being very tender and careful in defence of its Inhabitants Liberties, Perſons, Eſtates and Lives from the Wills and Arbitrary Power of lawleſs unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Men; and every Engliſh man hath a Birth right and Inheritance in this Law; and it is the Juſt Intereſt of every honeſt man, to endeavour to keep up this Standard and Bulwork of Property, Lives and Liberties againſt all that would invade them, or attempt to rob and ſpoil them of either.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, there is much Failure and Corruption in the Executive Part of this well framed <hi>law</hi> and <hi>government,</hi> &amp; there is ſo much Partiality, Self-intereſt and Iniquity got into the Place and Seat of Judgment, that many times the clear Stream and Current of Juſtice and Equity is ſtopped, defiled and corrupted, and it's a very hard thing for a poor man, who is oppreſſed and abuſed by his Neighbour, to get Relief; but this is not to be attributed to the Law, but to the Abuſers and Corrupters of it, whoſe Work is to pervert the End of all good Law and Government, which is <hi>to be a Terror to the Evil-doers, and a Praiſe to them that do well;</hi> where-ever this juſt End is not anſwered, ſuch do not rule nor judge for God, let them pretend what they will,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60088:3"/>but are Contemners, Deſpiſers and Perverters of the Law of God, and all good men.</p>
            <p>In this Caſe of ours we apprehend our ſelves Arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (contrary to Law) impoſed upon by a ſort of raſh incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate men who have run themſelves upon a Work more proper for a <hi>Parliament</hi> then a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> and if they had a Reward accordingly, they would receive but their deſert; and it being to do a Work illegal and ſo
<note n="‖" place="margin">For the Truth of this we may appeal to the Conſciences of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Inhabitants of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Pariſh, whether they &amp; their Neighbours were not more ſober, temperate, grave and wiſe, and guilty of leſs ſin and Tranſgreſſion againſt God and man twenty or thirty years ago, then at this time; if ſo, then wherein are people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by the ſtudied Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Hirelings?</note> needleſs and unprofitable to our ſelves and Neighbours, we were willing to ſtop their Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Proceeds, otherwiſe we ſhould have been paſſive, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſuffered the weight of the leaden Hands of unholy Church, whoſe Mercies are very Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; witneſs the Popiſh Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and cruel Torture and Burnings of conſcientious men, and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Goals, Whips, Stocks, Cutting off Ears and Stigmatizing, and Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo, as in <hi>New-England,</hi> upon the account of Church, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Worſhip; all which we teſtifie againſt, as directly contrary to, and inconſiſtent with the Pure Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Church of Chriſt, as is ſignified in ſhort in what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; but is according to the Whore, or falſe Church, whoſe Weapons are carnal, and not ſpiritual, who is and hath been ſince the Apoſtacy very buſie in Chriſtendom in ſpoiling peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Goods, impriſoning and torturing their Bodies, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60088:3"/>ſometimes killing them alſo, and making her ſelf drunk with the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>Now, it's ſo far from the Nature and Life of the true Church to inflict Corporal Puniſhments for Spiritual Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or to hurt any man's Liberty, Perſon and Eſtate in this World, about the things of the World to come, as Faith, Conſcience and Manner of Worſhip, that it is both unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and unreaſonable; for if People do err in their minds, and underſtand things relating to their future Eſtate amiſs, and are of an unſound Judgment in the things of God, and in matters relating to his Kingdom, &amp;c. Spiritual-weapon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, and not Goalers and Executioners of <hi>corporal Puniſhments,</hi> are to deal with ſuch People, and inform and reſtore them with the Spirit of Love and Meekneſs, if they can, according to the Example and Doctrine of Chriſt Jeſus his Apoſtles and primitive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who never uſed <hi>outward Force</hi> and <hi>Violence,</hi> or <hi>corporal Puniſhments</hi> to compel People to be of their Religion; <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> came not this way into the World, neither is it, or ever was it upheld or propagated by ſuch means; it's a Goſpel of Life and Salvation, and brings Peace on Earth, and Good Will to Men; and the true <hi>Miniſters</hi> of it being endued with Power from on High, in the univerſal Love of God perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded men to be reconciled to him, by turning them from the Darkneſs within to the Light and Grace of God Within from the Power of Satan within, by which their minds were captivated, to the Spirit and Power of God within, <hi>that they might receive Remiſſion of their Sins, and Inheritance among them that are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if people would not receive them into their Houſes, or build them ſome Houſes to preach this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60088:4"/>to them in, they were not to call for Fire from Heaven upon them, nor ſend their Bodies to Goal, or take away or ſpoil them of their Earthly Treaſures, becauſe they would not receive their heavenly Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, nor own and believe them to be Diſpenſers and miniſters of it;</hi> let all that pretend themſelves to be Chriſt's Miniſters compare themſelves herewith.</p>
            <p>And let this be conſidered by every true <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, That if the <hi>raſh, inconſiderate, unlawful Proceeds</hi> of a few of our Neighbours becomes <hi>preſidential,</hi> and eſcapes Correction, which is ſo direct againſt the fundamental Law of our Country, others may take Boldneſs to rate and raiſe Eighteen Thouſand Pound as well as Eighteen Hundred Pound upon the like Pretence.</p>
            <p>But we attribute this Favour and Connivance to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Influence of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority,</hi> whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and nature is to creep over the Heads of Law and Goſpel too, and to ſit as a Queen over mens <hi>Perſons, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Lives and Eſtates;</hi> ſo that if people pleaſe not the Church (or that Sect or Sort of men, that in a Nation or Country calls themſelves ſo, and hath the Power in their hand, then all that's contrary is lyable to Ruin by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Influence of holy Church, (falſly ſo called) being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no other then the great Whore, which <hi>John</hi> ſaw ſit upon the Waters, and ride upon the Scarlet-coloured Beaſt.</p>
            <p>For it hath been the Work of the falſe Church for many <hi>ages</hi> and <hi>generations</hi> paſt, and is her endeavour at this day, to get upon the <hi>backs</hi> of <hi>Lords, Dukes, Kings</hi> and <hi>Emperors,</hi> and other <hi>great men</hi> of the Earth, and to lead them which way ſhe pleaſeth; and ſhe arrayeth her ſelf in ſuch beautiful Apparel, and giveth her ſelf ſuch glorious <hi>Titles,</hi> and holds forth ſuch a glorious <hi>Cup,</hi> that through
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60088:4"/>the Myſtery of Iniquity, that works in her, they are ſo far deceived and intoxicated, that they think and are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>ſhe is the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt;</hi> and ſo many <hi>mighty men</hi> and <hi>Monarchs</hi> of the Earth, in this part of the World called <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> eſpecially, are as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to her, and as tractable under her, as a Beaſt is under its Rider, and ready to do any Drudgery for her.</p>
            <p>And this is obſervable, That if any of theſe become ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the Weight of their Burden, and to ſee what a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity they have upon their <hi>Backs,</hi> and begin to be weary and unwilling to carry it any longer, then ſuch a one, let him be Lord, Duke, King or Emperor, if her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Senſures, Curbs and Threats, will not ſerve to bring him again into Obedience to holy Church, ſhe will get his Blood to drink, if ſhe can, as might be inſtanced at large by many Examples.</p>
            <p>It's ſaid, That it is a Maxime in the Church of Rome, <hi>not to keep Faith with ſuch ſhe accounts Hereticks, longer then till ſhe hath an Advantagious Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to break it;</hi> and that ſhe is very ready with her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations to abſolve <hi>Subjects</hi> from their <hi>Obedience</hi> to their Natural Prince and Governour, if they judge him an Enemy to holy Church: if this Report and Saying be true, we declare it a Curſed Opinion, and Inconſiſtent with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society and the Well-being of Mankind, and an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Mark and Sign of the Whore, Beaſt and Falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and not of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And if the Church of <hi>England</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtants</hi> be of the mind and Opinion of Doctor <hi>Parr,</hi> that when People differ in their Judgments and Underſtandings about ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Matters, and are tender and Conſcientious, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conform to their Way of Worſhip, and have the Nick
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60088:5"/>Reproachful Name of a <hi>Quaker</hi> given them (as the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had that of a <hi>Nazarine</hi>) though they live never ſo Soberly, Righteouſly, Juſtly, Uprightly and Inoffenſively among their Neighbours and all people, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the things of a Man, that notwithſtanding this, <hi>SUCH ARE NO SUBJECTS OF THE KING,</hi> which in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> implyes thus much, that the King nor Law is not concerned to defend their Lives, Liberties nor Eſtates; but that, becauſe they are out of the Pale of their Church, they ought to lie open to the Mouth of every Raveuous Beaſt and Devourer. So far as the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> are tainted with this Opinion, they are guided and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the ſame ſpirit of Darkneſs, Ignorance and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, and in the Ground is one with the other, and the ſame evil Effects and cruel Conſequences attend it; for that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Sect or Opinion that will take upon them to <hi>abſolve</hi> Kings and Governours, and the Judges of the Law, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concern'd in Duty to adminiſter Juſtice and take a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Care of Harmleſs Innocent People, that dwell within their Dominions, becauſe they are not of the ſame mind about Religion, nor do not conform to their Church-Diſcipline; we ſay, it is the ſame ſpirit of Deceit and Deluſion with that which pretends a Power to abſolve Subjests from their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Superiours, and is alſo inconſiſtent with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society, Cruel, Unnatural, Bloody and Unreaſonable: Let ſuch as are concerned therein Repent thereof; for they have not the Spirit of Chriſt ruling in their Hearts, though they may have his Name in their Mouthes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60088:5"/>
            <head>Here follows a Copy of a Letter ſent to Dr. <hi>Parr,</hi> and the reſt concerned, in which was encloſed a Copy of the Subſtance of what follows.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Doctor Parr,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Encloſed we ſend thee, before we communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it further, that if thee, or any of the reſt whom it doth concern, can except againſt or diſprove any thing thereof, as relating to matter of Fact, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, you have your liberty or opportunity to ſignifie the ſame; for when your forty dayes are ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pired, we expect the end of your work deſigned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us to be ſoon accompliſhed, that is, to have our Bodies in Goal, from our Wives, Children, Trades and Families, which is a work of Cruelty, and not of Chriſtianity: and know this, the Cry of the Innocent will enter the Ears of the Lord againſt you; and if you ſhall be ſuffered to make our Wives Widdows, and our Children Fatherleſs, though we can forgive you, yet it is juſt with the Lord if he meaſure the ſame meaſure to you again; for the Blood of the Righteous will cry, as <hi>Abel</hi>'s did, and Vengeance will purſue the Evil-doer, and you ſhall be juſtly charged as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi> charged the profeſſing <hi>Jews, Mic.</hi> 3.10. <hi>They build up</hi> Sion <hi>with Blood, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity:</hi> (read the whole Chapter, which indeed is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to <hi>England,</hi> as truly as ever it was to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Jews</hi>) And let this be conſidered, that if you polute and ſtain your Church-building with the Blood of the Innocent, through Impriſonment in naſty Holes, and put them out of a Capacity to provide Bread for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60088:6"/>their VVives and Children, this will ſo defile you and your Temple, that the Biſhop of this Dioceſs, nor all the Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> will not be able to remove and take it away by all the power of Conſecration they have; and the ſtones in the VVall ſhall witneſs againſt you in the Day of Account.</p>
            <p>Now, for the Cauſes mentioned in the firſt page, we do intend to make your VVork publick, that all may ſee what ſpirit rules in thine and your Hearts, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding your talk and profeſſion of Chriſt and Chriſtianity, and that you concerned may be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced concerning the Evil of your proceeds againſt us (ſeeing it is matter of Conſcience unto us) and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thereof, and decline the proſecuting that which the ſpirit of Enmity and Violence (and not the ſpirit of Chriſt) would lead you to; ſo would you bring forth Fruits more becoming the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> which is the Deſire of your <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Neighbours,</hi> whoſe daily endeavour and practice is, to ſhun the way of the wicked, and to avoid the Path of evil men, and to live in that <hi>Love</hi> which teacheth to deſire the good of all, and the fall and hurt of none; and herein our ſleep is ſweet, and our reſt is pleaſant, even as we hate the <hi>bread of wickedneſs</hi> and the <hi>wine of violence;</hi> and this is the Path of the Juſt, which is as a ſhining Light, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning more and more unto the perfect day; but the way of the wicked is Darkneſs, they know not at what they ſtumble.</p>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>Parr,</hi> know this, If thou madeſt choice of thoſe words in the 4th chapter of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> verſ. 14, 15, 16. for thy Text the Day thy <hi>Excommunication</hi> was read againſt us (as is at leaſt ſuppoſed) as if they did concern us, or were applicable upon us, thou art
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60088:6"/>greatly miſtaken; for we have not only talked of and profeſſed the Light, Law, Grace and Spirit of Truth, but received the ſame, learn't of &amp; walked in the ſame, and are guided thereby out of the Path and Way of the Wicked, and out of the ſpirit of envy, evil-wil, miſchief and violence againſt any man's Perſon, Life, Liberty or Eſtate; it would be well for you if thee, nor none of thy Flock, were found in thoſe ſteps: not farther to enlarge, only remember and conſider this one ſaying written in the 5th of the <hi>Proverbs, The Wayes of a Man are before the Eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> if this Sctipture, with that which ſaith, <hi>Men ſhall give an Account of their Deeds done in the Body, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Good or Evil,</hi> were truly weighed and believed by all that read them, it would put a ſtop to the Worker of Iniquity, and quench the Spirit of Violence and Cruelty, Prejudice and Evil, and Meekneſs, Love and Righteouſneſs would grow and encreaſe amongſt our Neighbours and Country-men, and Peace, Quietneſs and good Neighbourhood would abound, which is indeed the Deſire of our Hearts and our daily Practice to promote, according to our ſtate and capacity, and can in Truth ſubſcribe our ſelves, <hi>Lovers of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and Haters of no man.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed on the behalf of the reſt of our Friends by us,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Otter,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Griffith Jones,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Torletonr,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Potter.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60088:7"/>
            <head>A BRIEF NARRATIVE Of the Proceedings of Doctor Parr, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>VVE the ſaid people being preſented and cited to the Biſhop's Court, made our Appearance, and according to the Priviledge and Right of every <hi>Engliſh</hi> man demanded a Copy of the Lybel formed againſt us, which was granted, and finding their proceeds were contrary to the known Law, and that the deſign of the Biſhop's Court was forth-with to <hi>curſe</hi> or <hi>excommunicate</hi> us out of their Church, and to caſt our Bodies into Jayle, did account it our Duty both as <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to endeavour to prevent the ſame, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly made motion by Council at the <hi>King's Bench Bar</hi> for a <hi>prohibition,</hi> which was not there poſitively denyed, but deferred; and we were adviſed by one of the Judges, <hi>To apply our ſelves fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Biſhop's Court, preſuming they would do as Right, as the Caſe did require; if not, then to
<note n="‖" place="margin">This commonly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth according to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Proverb, <hi>Out of the Frying-Pan into the Fire.</hi>
                  </note> appeal to the Arches or Delegates.</hi> So upon this his Preſumption, that the Biſhop's Court would do us Right (or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was willing to pleaſe the <hi>Prieſts</hi>) refuſed to grant a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition.</p>
            <p>Then being left to the Mercy of the Biſhop's Court, we again received Citations to appear, and did appear accordingly divers times; but finding our lawful Exceptions againſt the Lybel, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60088:7"/>all we could offer and plead, though never ſo juſt and according to their own Law, ſleighted and over-ruled, and our ſelves pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced excommunicate by a Perſon who declared himſelf <hi>Ignorant in the Matter</hi> (but willing to <hi>fulfil the Deſign of the Court</hi>) for they refuſed to receive our Anſwers under our <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> by <hi>proxy</hi> rendered, which according to Law and the Rules of their own Court they ought to have received; but perceiving they had to do with a People that made Conſcience of keeping that eminent Precept and Command of Chriſt [SWEAR NOT AT ALL] and ſeeing their other <hi>gins</hi> and <hi>traps</hi> were too weak to hold them, and to ſtop their Paſſage towards Relief at Common Law, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reſolved to make this occaſion of <hi>refuſing to Swear</hi> the Colour and Ground to pronounce us <hi>excommunicate</hi> for <hi>contempt to their Court,</hi> though we had ſhewed Diligence to appear time after time, according to their <hi>citations</hi> and <hi>arbitrary ſummons</hi> in their own <hi>name</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> and had anſwered them in all their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, ſo far as lawfully they might, both as Men and <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> And the <hi>diſhonour</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> of their Court is on their own parts, occaſioned and contracted by their own evil doing, in trampling upon the Law and the Legal Right of others, yea, and the Rules and Preſidents of their own Court (though called <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi>) when they ſtand in the way of their own Intereſt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, as in this particular Caſe is proved true by Experience.</p>
            <p>So contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt (whoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Servants they pretend to be) they would compel people to <hi>ſwear,</hi> and ſo break his Command; and if they refuſe, call it <hi>contempt to their Court,</hi> pronounce them <hi>excommunicate,</hi> and get their Bodies into <hi>Goal,</hi> ſeparate <hi>Husband</hi> and <hi>Wife, Father</hi> and <hi>Children, Maſter</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> put all Relations out of a Capacity to ſerve one another according to the Law of Nature and Grace, and all about a Matter of Conſcience, this is neither like Chriſt nor <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but unnatural and inhumane: And you have not ſhewed forth the Qualifications of <hi>ſpiritual Men</hi> or <hi>good Chriſtians,</hi> but do clearly demonſtrate your ſelves to be ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, carnal, unjuſt and unreaſonable, and great Strangers to that Royal Law of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>As you would have others do to you, ſo do you unto them;</hi> ſuch Doings will never convince any that you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60088:8"/>are indeed what you have a Name to be, but rather confirm them in their preſent Perſwaſions: And if you by your Threats, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and injuſtice fright any out of Tenderneſs of Conſcience, and bring them through fear of ſuffering into an <hi>outward conformity to your Church and Worſhip,</hi> know this, <hi>you make them two-fold more the Children of Hellthen before:</hi> Outward <hi>force, violence</hi> and <hi>compulſion</hi> may make <hi>hypocrites,</hi> but no <hi>true Chriſtians;</hi> it may change the <hi>manners,</hi> but not the <hi>mind,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It might be well if you <hi>ſpiritual men,</hi> ſo called, would ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider, whether your Self-intereſt [and not the Love and Care of Souls] be not the ground of your Church and Court Proceedings, ſeeing <hi>Money</hi> will ſatisfie for all <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>trangreſſions</hi> againſt you and your Church, as in your Mother Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Whenas indeed all the bodily Exerciſe, together with all the Gold and Silver in the World, is not able nor ſufficient to expiate or ſatisfie for one ſin committed againſt God, Chriſt and the true Church; neither did the true Church in any Age ſince <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> was in the World, ever abſolve or acquit ſins and tranſgreſſion againſt her for <hi>Money:</hi> It's time to conſider your way, and amend, and ceaſe to exerciſe <hi>deceit</hi> and <hi>violence</hi> over the People for <hi>ſelfiſh ends;</hi> and if you have no better Way, Means and Arguments to inform perſwade and convince people, that you are of the True Church, becauſe you have Power and Compulſive Laws on your ſide, and can deſtroy their Liberty, Eſtate and Lives through ſtreight Impriſonment in <hi>naſty Goals</hi> (this being the Way and Means of the Falſe Church, whoſe Weapons are and were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes Carnal) there are a People whom God hath raiſed up in this Age, and inſtructed in the pure Chriſtian Religion, whoſe <hi>goods</hi> you may ſpoyl, whoſe <hi>bodies</hi> you may torture and impriſon, and whoſe <hi>blood</hi> you may drink alſo, ſooner then force and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them by your <hi>unchriſtian means</hi> to become conformable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to your Church.</p>
            <p>Now we ſeeing our ſelves thus abuſed, and that they over-run the <hi>Rules of their own Court,</hi> to haſten us into <hi>Goal,</hi> we again mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for a <hi>Prohibition</hi> at the <hi>Exchequer-Bar,</hi> and the chief Banon ſhewed himſelf <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>moderate,</hi> and was ready to grant the ſame, their Council refuſing to plead further in their behalf, their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60088:8"/>own <hi>Lybel</hi> ſaying, that <hi>the greater part or ſome part of the Pariſh made the Rate,</hi> diſſatiſfied their Council, and would then plead no further, only prayed time till the firſt day of the next Term, which was the ſecond inſtant, betwixt which time, as the ſequel plainly proves, Doctor <hi>Parr</hi> with other had made way ſo far in the matter, by deviſed untrue Allegations and other wayes, that our Requeſt of a <hi>Prohibition</hi> might not be anſwered; for when our Council pleaded, they were very much diſcountenanced by ſome of the Judges with <hi>Words, Nods</hi> and <hi>Frowns;</hi> and though they pleaded Law in the caſe, it was not regarded; only the chief Baron ſhewed himſelf very juſt and impartial, and declared his Opinion, <hi>That a Prohibition did property lie in the caſe; but ſeeing his Brethren were of another Opinion, he ſhould leave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, it is to be obſerved, that the Court could not without man feſt partiality deny a <hi>Prohibition,</hi> until <hi>falſe Allegations</hi> were deviſed, and pleaded in open Court to overturn our Suggeſtion; therefore Doctor <hi>Parr,</hi> with the reſt, had by Untrue Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Large Fee (or to uſe ſome of their own words, <hi>Large Grezing</hi>) fitted and prepared their Council to plead very grand Lyes or Untruths, and produced an <hi>Oath</hi> in Court, together with the Witneſs and Teſtimony of Doctor <hi>Parr</hi> to affirm to the ſame.</p>
            <p>The particular Lyes were as followeth; Firſt, <hi>That there was a Neceſsity to pull down the ſaid Church, the Pillars being Wood, bowed and rotten, the Roof and South Wall ready to fall, many being hurt and wounded with the fall of part of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That Dr.</hi> Parr <hi>and ſome others did contract with the Workmen for</hi> 120 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>to build the Chancel, South-Porch &amp; new Enlang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and he and others paid diſtinctly for thoſe parts, and that it was not included in the Pariſh-Rate, himſelf giving Fifty pound part of the Hundred and Twenty pound agreed for the Building the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That all the Pariſhioners, yea, every man, were ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and had all paid their Money, only Twenty Four</hi> Quakers; <hi>and that the whole Aſſeſment upon them was not above Forty pound, the greateſt amongſt them being not above Fifty ſhillings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, with other things to the ſame effect, being affirmed as with a Face of Braſs in open Court, though great Untruths, yet
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60088:9"/>great Credit (we judge, by reaſon of the Preſence and Teſtimony of Doctor <hi>Parr</hi>) was by three of the four Judges given to them, and all that could be urged to the contrary rejected and ſleighted; and though by our Council we much preſſed to go to Tryal, &amp; if we did not prove our Suggeſtion, we would give them Coſt; yet nothing that could be ſaid on our parts would prevail, the burthen of the Plea againſt us being, NONE BUT <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS,</hi> MY LORD; NONE BUT TWENTY FOUR <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS,</hi> MY LORD: As if, when people have the Nick-Name of a <hi>Quaker</hi> put upon them, they then loſe all their Right, and forfeit all their Priviledges as Men, and the Benefit of the Law of their Native Country; as if, to have the Frowns of the Church, were ſufficient to turn them out of the Protection of the King, Law and Government, and to have their Liberties, Eſtates and Lives expoſed to Ruin; and that Dr. <hi>Parr</hi> is of this Opinion, appears by his own words ſpeaking that day, being the ſecond of the third Moneth called <hi>May,</hi> to one in this manner and words, THAT THE <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi> WERE NONE OF THE KING's SUBJECTS.</p>
            <p>This Saying doth not become a man of his Profeſſion; it ſhews plainly what ſpirit rules in his Heart under all his Talk of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> he is a great way off the Mind and Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe Miniſter or Servant he pretends to be. It may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid of him as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.54.</note> who deſired to have Liberty to command Fire to come down from Heaven to deſtroy thoſe that would not receive him, it's ſaid, <hi>He turned, and rebuked them, and ſaid, they knew not what ſpirit they were of; for the Son of Man came not to deſtroy men's Lives, but to ſave them;</hi> and his Diſciples and Miniſters indeed are of the ſame Mind and Spirit now. But what would this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Opinion do with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſuch as do not comply with his Mind and Underſtanding in and about Matters of Church and Worſhip? Let him ſeriouſly conſider the extent thereof, this unnatural bloody Conceit of his, (viz.) <hi>That if people pleaſe not the Prieſts, or tranſgreſs againſt their Church, then they ceaſe to be the King's Subjects, and loſe their Birth-right as men, and the Benefit of the Law of their Native Country:</hi> Would not this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60088:9"/>Notion &amp; Judgment of his lead him into that Ravenous Appetite which ſome Prieſts had in the Prophets dayes, which he compared to Dogs, yea, greedy dumb Dogs, that could never have enough, (bear the Roughneſs of the Speech being they are the Prophet's words) read verſ. 10 and 11. of the 56th chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and ſee if <hi>England</hi> doth not abound with ſuch blind, ignorant, rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Watchmen there ſpoken againſt, who, when people put not into their Mouthes, they prepare War againſt them; ſuch there were in the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi>'s time, and ſuch there are now in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> that preach for Hire, and divine for Money, &amp;c. read the third chapter of <hi>Micah</hi>'s Prophecy againſt the Cruelty of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Falſhood of Prophets and Prieſts, that cauſe people to err, and that bite with their Teeth, and cry <hi>peace</hi> ſo long as people feed them.</p>
            <p>Indeed Dr. <hi>Parr</hi>'s Moderation and peaceable Behaviour hath hitherto been noted and commended, in that he hath not thrown ſo many into Goal for <hi>Tythes</hi> as he might, nor perſecuted Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that dwell within his Pariſhes for <hi>not Worſhipping in the ſame Manner, Form and Way as he doth:</hi> But now one of his Pariſhes has more in it preſented for not coming to Church (and as is ſaid, to be proceeded againſt by the Statute of 20<abbr>l.</abbr> a Moneth) and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated for not Repairing their Church, then all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in and about <hi>London:</hi> ſo that if he gives farther place to this unnatural Opinion of his (<hi>That people ceaſe to be Subjects to the King when they are called</hi> Quakers) it will quickly lead him out of all his Moderation and ſeeming Tenderneſs, and his Mouth will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen wide enough to ſwollow down their Bodies, Liberties, Lives and Eſtates; and if his Church's Curſe was powerful enough, would ſend their Souls to Hell alſo. This would be the Work of a ſad Paſtour; who is found in it, cannot be a Watcher for the good of Souls, nor a good Shepherd, that careth naturally for the Sheep; but are found Watchers for Gain from their Quarter, and for the Fleece: And it is an infallible Mark, Sign and Demonſtration of a Miniſter of Antichriſt, Falſe Prophet and Deceiver, to declare, <hi>That people ought not to live in peace, and enjoy their Liberty and property, and benefit of the Law of their native Country, as Subjects of the King, except they will be his Diſciples, or members of his Church,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60088:10"/>repair the ſame, and put into his mouth alſo;</hi> theſe are ſuch as ſerve their own Bellies, and not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but are a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal and Reproach to the Chriſtian-Religion while they profeſs themſelves Miniſters of it. But the <hi>nakedneſs, greedineſs, covetouſneſs, enviouſneſs, deceitfulneſs</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> of the <hi>prieſthood</hi> appears more and more daily, and is obvious to Thouſands and Ten Thouſands of people in this our native Country of <hi>England,</hi> who make a <hi>trade</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>learn to be Preachers of the Goſpel</hi> (as they ſay) as a Man learns to make Shoes; they learn and buy their Skill of Preaching of Man; and they not only ſell it again to their free Cuſtomers, that willingly buy, but they impoſe the ſale and exact the price of others that dwell within their Quarter, though they like them not, nor will have none of their Ware; this is a ſore Evil in the Prieſthood, and a great Burden upon the people. So much by the way.</p>
            <p>But to proceed to ſhew the truth of our Plea, and the groſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Adverſaries lyes. Firſt, there was not a neceſſity to pull down ſo much as was pulled down; neither was a danger of its ſudden fall, as was pretended, the wooden Pillars were moſtly Sound; and the Roof and Walls might have been Repaired and Amended according to our ſugeſtion, for Three or Four Hundred Pound: Only you would have it Fine, and Beautiful and honourable Vaults; for when ſome urged to have it Repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not pulled down, (it is ſaid) <hi>D. P.</hi> anſwered, <hi>What did they think he would Preach in a patched Church, or have a place propt up with Prongs and Forks?</hi> So that if we could have had Liberty, we could have anſwered the chief Baron's Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very fully; which Queſtion was, <hi>Whether there were any thing done more out of Curioſſity, then of Neceſſity?</hi> Secondly, there was no Contract made, nor ſo much as propounded to be made with the Maſter Work-man for the new Foundation work, ſouth Porth <hi>Chancel</hi> nor <hi>Vaults,</hi> diſtinct and ſeparate from the reſt of the Work, before the rate was made, and your <hi>Lybel</hi> formed againſt us; but all was Included together in one Bargain. And the Rate mentioned in your <hi>Lybel</hi> is ſufficient to pay for all, if Collected: And that this your Plea and invented Lye, took
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60088:10"/>beginning ſince you ſaw that you had out gone the Biſhop's-order, any Preſident or Law either: And that, what hath been done through Curioſſity, hath occaſioned great part of the Charge. And your pleading an agreement with the Work-man for One Hundred and Twenty Pound for the ſaid work, was a late for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged device to baffle and prevent the Courſe of Juſtice. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, every Man in the Pariſh were not ſatisfied nor Conſenting to what was done: Neither had every one paid their Money, but Twenty Four <hi>Quakers:</hi> Neither is Fifty Shillings the greateſt Sum Rated upon any <hi>Quaker,</hi> nor Forty Pound the whole Sum laid upon them, ſome being above Six Pound, and the Sum rated upon them about One Hundred Pound: And more then a Hundred that pay to the Poor beſides <hi>Quakers,</hi> did not conſent to the ſame: So this is a four-fold Lye. And ſeeing you have by corrupt Intereſt and Lyes, ſtopped the Currant of Juſtice, you have no cauſe to rejoyce, nor ring Bells for Joy, the conſideration how you have come by, and accompliſhed your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, truly weighed in a ſerious Spirit, and Meaſured by the rule of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> of which you have a Profeſſion, is really a great cauſe of Sorrow: and when you come to give an Account of your Deeds done in the Body, you ſhall be ſenſible thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> practice was, to rejoyce in the Truth and not in Iniquity, and to ſpeak the Truth, every man to his Neighbour, and to bear falſe witneſs againſt none, and deſpiſe diſhoneſt Gain, or the gain of Oppreſſion, and to do as they would be done by: Never ſo much as attempting to Compel ſuch as did not believe nor receive their Doctrine, nor own them as true Miniſters, or a true Church to Contribute to their Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or to Build or Repair their Meeting-places. Neither Law nor Goſpel doth afford you any Preſident or Example for ſuch a practice; you are faine to make uſe of ſuch Laws and Cna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos as were made in the dark Night of Popery, to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize you in ſuch kind of work. You deny the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> in Words, but imitate them in Practice, and make uſe of all their Laws and Cuſtoms in being (as you have occaſion) to ſerve your Intereſt, and defend you in your Trade of <hi>preaching</hi> for <hi>Money, praying</hi> and <hi>Singing</hi> for <hi>Money, Chriſtening, Churching</hi> and <hi>Bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60088:11"/>for <hi>Money, Selling Abſolutions</hi> and <hi>Licences</hi> for <hi>Money;</hi> and for <hi>Money</hi> a Man may get into your <hi>Church</hi> again, after he is <hi>Curſed</hi> out, or <hi>Excommunicate;</hi> and for Money a Man may purchaſe any part of your Religion; yea, for Money a Man may have Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Sermon made for him after he is Dead; but without <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> it's hard to get any thing of the <hi>Prieſthood; not a Child Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened, nor a Corpes buried without Money</hi> by many Prieſts, though the perſons concerned, have ſcarce enough to buy them Bread; theſe and ſuch like covetous Practices of the Prieſthood, together with the Unchriſtian-like Converſation of their people makes the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> ſtink among <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that Religion and Religious practices that is or can be bought or ſold for Money, is an Abomination in the ſight of the Lord, and Relected by all tender-hearted Conſcientious People. And it is a grief to many, to obſerve and behold how thoſe called <hi>proteſtants</hi> do follow the Example, and Imitate that dark Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Sect of the <hi>papiſts;</hi> who ſell their Maſſes, Pardons, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions and Diſpenſations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Money; ſo the <hi>proteſtants</hi> Pray, Sing, Preach, Abſolve, and ſell Licences for Money; who are only changed in Name, Manner, Form, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſome outſide Practices, but not in Nature and Life; the ſame Spirit of <hi>Cain, Core,</hi> Falſe Prophet, Idol Shepherd, Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Money Diviner, <hi>Pilate,</hi> chief Prieſt, Judas; and the reſt of that Generation, mentioned and teſtified againſt in the holy Scriptures, Rules and Reigns in the Hearts of the formal <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> as in the <hi>papiſts;</hi> and it is to the Heart, the inſide that God looks: And all true Reformation begins within, in the Heart, if that be, and continue Corrupted, Deceitful and Deſeparately wicked; Unpurged, Uncleanſed, and Unſanctified by the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood and Life of Jeſus, all Names, and outſide Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Worſhips, and Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are of no worth, nor acceptable in the ſight of God, according to Chriſt's teaching in the Sixth Chapter of <hi>Luke,</hi> 43.44, 45. verſ. <hi>A good Tree bringeth not forth corrupt fruit; neither doth a corrupt Tree bring forth good fruit, every Tree is known by his fruit, for of Thorns men do not gather figgs, nor of a Bramble-buſh gather they Grapes: A good man out of the good Treaſure of his Heart, bringeth forth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60088:11"/>that which is good, an Evil man out of the Evil Treaſure of his Heart, bringeth forth that which is Evil; for out of the abundance of the Heart, his mouth ſpeaketh; the Tree muſt be good, the Heart purged, ere the fruit can be good or well-pleaſing to God.</hi> So it is not a changing from one Opinion to another, or from the Form of the <hi>Romiſh Prelacy,</hi> to that of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or from that to <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> or from any one Sect to another, is of any worth, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God; 'tis the turning from Darkneſs to Light, from Sin to Righteouſneſs, from the Power of Satan to the Power of God; it is the Greation of a clean Heart, and the renewing of a right Spirit, it is to know the inſide cleanſed, and then the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide will be clean alſo: Theſe are the things that are of an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity, and of great Worth, and this to know and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will ſtand People in ſtead in the Day of the Lord, when all Formallity and outſide Worſhip among all the Sects in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> will vaniſh away like Smoak, this will ſtand and abide: And theſe are the true Worſhippers of God, in the Spirit and in the Truth, who Experimentally know the Power, Vertue, and Opperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit of Truth in their own Hearts, Minds and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, making them free from that which did defile, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and darken them: Theſe are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> indeed, <hi>Jews</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward indeed; all others are but <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in Name, let their Profeſſion and Form of Religion be what it will.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, we being denyed a <hi>prohibition</hi> at the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer Court,</hi> through corrupt Intereſt, and the falſe Allegations before mentioned, we moved by two Councels at the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas Bar,</hi> who pleaded and urged their own Law to ſhew that of Right, A <hi>Prohibition</hi> ought to be granted, like men of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; but the ſame untruth as was urged at the <hi>Exchequer Court</hi> being pleaded again, and that Sentence, NONE BUT <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KERS,</hi> MY LORD; NONE BUT TWENTY FOUR <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KERS,</hi> MY LORD; being often repeated, that Sentence ſeemed enough to turn all againſt us; ſo no <hi>Prohibition</hi> could be obtained, though offer was made to go to Tryal in few dayes; yea, the Council deſired but two dayes to prove our ſuggeſtion or give them Coſt, but all in vain, nothing could prevail, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe we were <hi>Quakers,</hi> or becauſe they were not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60088:12"/>to offend the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Authority, is not certain; in the Prieſts Hands they found us, and there they ſeemed reſolved to leave us, till they had wrought their Wills upon us, and ſitted us for a Jayle; and becauſe they were greedy to effect the ſame, and not willing to looſe any time, they proceeded the very next day to publiſh their Excommunication in their Meeting-place, commonly called a <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> (but by ſome of their own Church, a <hi>Smock-Houſe,</hi> becauſe Built by a Collection among Women) in ſome time they found they had committed an Errour in their haſte, in reading their <hi>Excommunication</hi> in this new Erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that it muſt be read in a place called a Church; and they having not any fit, and Conſecrated in their own Pariſh, leſt their Fathers work of Violence and Perſecution ſhould looſe time they procured their Curſe to be publiſhed in another old Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe hard by, ſtanding in the ſame County. And now the next thing they wait for, is, the end of the mercy of the Statute Law which allows Forty Dayes at leaſt, in favour of every Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated perſon, ere the Prieſts can get a Writ to throw their Bodies into Jayle. It is much to be queſtioned, whether the Mercy of <hi>Eccleſiſtical Courts</hi> would extend to forty hours; did not the Statute Law put a check upon them; yet theſe Courts are made up of the Principal Members of their Church, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Spiritual Men, ſuch as have entred into holy Orders; but what Spirit, Church and Order they are of, their Fruits ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declare to all that are not wilfully blind. And all People may Pray, <hi>From the Biſhops Courts and unreaſonable men, Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, let all concerned in the Pariſh of <hi>Mary Magdalen's,</hi> who have given out ſuch unchriſtian Words, and cruel Threats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Quakers; as that they would ſend them to the Devil; and that they ſhould lie in Jayle and Rot; and that they would Ride many miles to ſee them Hanged; and that they ſhould be proſecuted for Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pound a Moneth, for not coming to Church; and to Ruin their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Trades, and not leave them a Bed to lie upon; and to prove them no Subjects to the King:</hi> Let ſuch Evil-minded men know, that the God whom they fear and ſerve, is able to deliver out of their Hands; but if he will not, know this, they are not careful to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60088:12"/>anſwer your Unrighteous Demands, nor bow to your corrupt Wills, nor Worſhip the Image you ſet up: And if the Lord ſhould deliver them into your Hands, as he did <hi>Job</hi> into the hand of the Devil; they are aſſured of this, that he will furniſh them with ſtrength and patience, to undergo all you ſhall be ſuffered to do againſt them: And as they abide with the Lord, and live in his Fear, his refreſhing Conſolating preſence will accompany them, and fill their Hearts with Joy, Peace, Content, and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, though without the pale of your Church, though in a naſty Priſon upon Straw, and out of the King's protection, and counted as the Off-ſcouring of all things, not fit to live in their native Country, as their Brethren the ancient Chriſtians were in Ages and Generations paſt: I ſay, as they ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake in Conſcience to God, &amp; not as Evil doers, they ſhall have the Anſwer of a good Conſcience, and enjoy the Preſence of the Lord, which is better then Life, and all thoſe things you threaten to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of; and they ſhall live the Life and dye the Death of the Righteous, and enter in and inherit the Crown of Life, when you that are of a bitter ſpirit, a perſecuting envious ſpirit (againſt your Neighbours, who have done you no Wrong) and yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt and Chriſtianity, ſhall ſee your ſelves ſhut out; and when <hi>trouble, anguiſh, ſorrow, pain, perplexity of ſpirit</hi> and <hi>horror of conſcience</hi> ſhall attend you in your Houſes and upon your Beds: for the Hand of God will lie heavy upon the Evil-doer and Cruel Men; and <hi>Vengeance is the Lord's, and he will repay it,</hi> and to him they can commit their Cauſe, and appeal to for Juſtice, ſeeing their Importunity (though like the poor Widow's to the Unjuſt Judge) cannot prevail with men.</p>
            <p>They are known (<hi>viz.</hi> the people called <hi>Quakers</hi>) to be a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, peaceable people among their Neighbours in all pariſhes, Towns, Cities and Countries where they dwell, throughout <hi>England;</hi> and great Obſervers and Honourers of the End of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy and true Chriſtian-Government, which is <hi>a praiſe to them that do well, and a terror to them that do evil;</hi> and are true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the King, and obedient to all the good and wholſom Laws of their native Country, which tend to preſerve men Liberties, Properties, Perſons and Eſtates, not for fear of Puniſhment, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60088:13"/>for Conſcience ſake; and they are ready to obey every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake, in all things relating to the Things of a Man, giving <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, and readily paying all Rates and Taxes that tend to the Good, and Service, and Preſervation of their Neighbours and Country-men, which is proper for any Chriſtian men to do; but in things relating to God and his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Conſcience, they cannot endure to be impoſed upon, they rather chuſe to obey God then Man in all ſuch Matters, and rather chuſe to ſuffer the ſpoiling of their Goods, impriſonment of their Bodies, and give up their Lives alſo, then ſubmit to the Wills and Commands of men in Matters of Religion, Church and Worſhip contrary to their Conſciences and the perſwaſions of the Spirit of God in their own Hearts, knowing <hi>it is a grievous thing to fall into the Hands of the living God, and to ſin againſt Light and Knowledge for fear of ſuffering;</hi> therein they would not only be like the Common Sinners of the Times (but worſe) who in their common Service daily confeſs, <hi>They do that which they ſhould not do, and leave undone that which they ſhould do,</hi> who confeſs <hi>they have no Health in them, but are full of putrified Sores from the crown of the Head to the ſole of the Foot:</hi> I ſay, they would be worſe then theſe (if worſe can be) and would be Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ſight of the Lord, and a Stink in his Noſtrils, and his Righteous Soul would be vexed with them from day to day, and they would not enjoy the Light of his Countenance, which to them is better then the encreaſe of Corn, Wine and Oyl.</p>
            <p>They can ſay, and that truly in the ſight of God, <hi>That they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the good of all men, and have Love and Good-wil to all their Neighbours and country-men, and can truly pray for their enemies, though they uſe them deſpightfully;</hi> and do deſire, <hi>they may ſee the evil of their wayes and repent, that they may enjoy Bleſsings and Peace temporal and eternal.</hi> And if any thing to the contrary, as Evil Thoughts, Evil Will, Prejudice or Enmity ariſe in them or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them againſt any, they judge it with the Light and Spirit of God, as an Evil inconſiſtent with their Profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and directly contrary to the Life and Nature thereof; for they have &amp; do declare &amp; own it their duty, to live &amp; walk accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, and to know the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60088:13"/>ſame written in their Hearts; and this Law was the Guide of Man-kind before Sin entred the World; before outward Laws were written in Tables of Stone, or in a Book. And thoſe that are led by this Law of the Spirit of Life, are the righteous Men and righteous Women; againſt whom there is no Law, being living Witneſſes of its power and vertue, making them free from that, and giving them Victory and Dominion over that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of which, the outward Law was added, <hi>viz.</hi> Sin: And theſe own all good Laws outwardly, and will not tranſgreſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. And the Law as ſaith <hi>Paul, Is not made for the Righteous, but for the Wicked,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10.</note> or Lawleſs and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient; for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and for Sinners; for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy and prophane; for murtherers of Fathers, and murtherers of Mothers; for man-ſlayers, for Whoremongers; for them that defile themſelves with mankind; for men-ſtealers, for Lyars, for perjured Perſons; and if there be any other thing that is contrary to ſound Doctrine, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whoever talks and profeſſes the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, and lives under the power of Sin and Death, (or continues in evil-doing) they are no true Subjects to it; nor lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of it, nor walkers in it; but a ſhame and a Scandal to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and Strangers and Alians from the Common-Wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Law of Sin and Death rules in their Minds and Members, and leads them Captive into Evil; and theſe are in great Bondage to the Luſt of the Eye, the Luſt of the Fleſh, and the Pride of Life: And theſe are the Children of diſobedience; in whoſe Hearts the Prince of the Air, the Prince of Darkneſs Rules, and leads them to Envy, Hate and Perſecute their Neighbours about Religion; which was never the work of a true Chriſtian: <hi>For he that hateth his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a man-ſlayer,</hi> 1 John 3.15. <hi>He that loveth not his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God, whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> 1 John 4.20.</p>
            <p>Be Serious, conſider your Work and Condition; and ſee how you ſtand in the ſight of God, and mind God's witneſs in your own Conſciences, and hearken to the Voice thereof; and it will Infallibly inform, and ſhew you whether the Spirit of Chriſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60088:14"/>and Chriſtianity, which is the Spirit of Meckneſs, Gentleneſs, Kindneſs, and Brotherly love, rules in your Hearts, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and the Voice of this, whether it be with you or againſt you, is as a Thouſand Witneſſes, and all that ſleight, and diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard its Voice, and ſtop their Ears at the Reproof thereof, while the day of their Viſitation laſts, Time will come upon them, and the Night will overtake them; wherein they ſhall hear its Voice whether they will or no, and be judged according thereto: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is compared to a Book; and the Deeds done in the Body are written therein. And the time will come upon them, when this Book ſhall be opened, and Men ſhall be judged according to what is written therein. And remember, the Teſtimony of a good, Conſcience both in the day of Health and Proſperity, and in the day of Sickneſs and Adverſity, in Life and Death, is of more vallue then all the World: And in any of theſe States and Conditions, a guilty defiled Conſcience, or a Conſcience that through cuſtom of doing Evil, becomes as Seared with a hot Iron; and a hard Heart, is a grievous Plague and ſore Judgment from God, and an inevitable ſign, and forerunner of Everlaſting Vengeance; and is indeed, the Fruit and Effect of Evil, or of ſleighting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing the voice of God's Witneſs, and the ſtriving of his Spirit in Peoples Hearts and Conſciences: But the anſwer and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a good Conſcience is of God; and is as a Well-ſpring of Life to thoſe that have it; where Bleſſings and Peace are enjoyed in the inward Man, amidſt of all Adverſity, Exerciſes and Tryals that may attend, both the outward and the inward; and ſuch can lie down in Peace, notwithſtanding all the Spirit of Enmity and Cruelty can work againſt them; whether it ariſe from an ignorant blind Zeal about Religion, Church and Worſhip; (as very much doth in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi>) not only againſt thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> but one Sect againſt another: Some of them being ſo full of Zeal, and ſo empty of Knowledge, that they think they do God Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to accompliſh the Ruin of ſuch as are not of their Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or whether it ariſe from corrupt Intereſt, Prejudice, and Evil will; the ground is one, though the end be various. The Lord give all People Wiſdom, to ſee their way out of the ſame; that they may be not only <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in Name and Profeſſion, but in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60088:14"/>Life and Nature: Then all Enmity, Cruelty and Violence would ceaſe, and Love, and Brotherly-kindneſs would abound: And then People would lie down like Lambs together, in that holy Mountain, (or Mountain of Holineſs) where no deſtroyer is, where no Violence, Cruelty, and Oppreſſion is: And this is the hearty deſire of every true Chriſtian, for their Neighbours and all People, who never were, nor ever will be found ſeeking the hurt or ruin of any man, threatning nor envying any, becauſe they conform not to the ſame ſort of Religion and Ceremonies that they are of. Whoever are found in this Spirit of Envy and Evil againſt their Neighbours and Country-men, about matters of Faith, Sacrifice and Worſhip, are of the Generation of <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt Envyer and Murtherer about Religion; and ſuch are not Chriſtians indeed; neither doth the Law of God, nor their Neighbours dwell in their Hearts, nor the Fruits of the Spirit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear and grow amongſt them; which Fruits are Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Temperance; againſt whom there is no Law; for the whole Law and the Prophets is fulfilled in this: <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart; and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> read <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37, 38, 39, 40. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.14. to the end of the Chapter; and the Lord prepare your Hearts to conſider what you read, that you may not only profeſs the holy Scriptures, but love and obey them, and receive that grace of which they teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; which taught and enabled the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> to live the Life of Holineſs they call for, and to avoid the contrary; that you may not alwayes be <hi>like ſilly Women laden with Sin, and led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with divers luſts, ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth, which makes free;</hi> but that you may know deliverance from the burthen of Sin, and bondage of Iniquity, and from the Luſts that lead aſide, and come to be made wiſe unto Salvation, and to feel the love of God ſpring in your Hearts; and Bleſſings and Peace attend you in your comings in, goings out, lyings down, and riſings up; even that Bleſſing and Peace, which the World cannot give nor take away.</p>
            <p>And that you and all people may come to inherit, poſſeſs and enjoy inward Peace with the Lord, and heavenly Conſolation in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60088:15"/>the Spirit, and Life everlaſting, is the hearty Deſire of your Friends and Neighbours, in Deriſion called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are redeemed from the ſpirit of Envy, hatred and Evil-will, from the ſpirit of Cruelty, Violence and Revenge, into that Love which deſires that Peace on Earth and Good-will to Men, may more and more encreaſe and abound; and ſo far as it is poſſible make it their daily Practice and Endeavour to live in Peace, and to follow Peace and Quietneſs with all men, according to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Chriſtian Religion, which whoſoever obeys and walks according thereto, are preſerved out of all Strife, Contention and Evil-Will, Prejudice, Enmity, Cruelty and Violence; and who ever are found bringing forth theſe Fruits, let their Talk and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Religion and Chriſtianity be never ſo great, they are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly corrupt Trees, and diſobedient Children, in whoſe Hearts the Enemy of God and Man rules, and they have not the Love of God and their Neighbour abiding in them, nor the Anſwer of a good Conſcience, neither are they Chriſtian indeed, though they profeſs the Name, which will ſtand none in ſtead in the Day of Account.</p>
            <p>Let all ſuch, to whom this may come, remember they have been told ſo, and it is the Word of Truth to them, whether they will hear or forbear.</p>
            <p>Now we, the <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) do ſolemnly teſtifie in the ſight of God, Angels and Men, <hi>That we do not refuſe to pay Tythes, to Repair old Maſs-Houſes (commonly and ignorantly called</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) <hi>or to pay Prieſts and Clarks Wages, Eaſter-Reckonings, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummer-Dues, and ſuch like, out of Wilfulneſs or Stubbornneſs, or out of any Enmity, Prejudice or Evil-will againſt any man's perſon whatſoever; but really and truly upon the Account of Conſcience to God, knowing and believing that we ſhould ſin againſt God, and the Light of his Spirit in our Hearts, and wound our own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in ſo doing.</hi> And we do upon the ſame account refuſe to <hi>come to thoſe old Maſs-houſes</hi> vulgarly called <hi>Churches,</hi> to hear a man of <hi>unclean lips</hi> and <hi>corrupt heart Say common Service to God, but Do none;</hi> read over <hi>common Prayer</hi> formally and cuſtomarily without the Spirit of Prayer; ſing <hi>David's Pſalms</hi> (turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60088:15"/>Meeter by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Fidlers or Muſicians) but not with the Spirit nor good Underſtanding; hear ſtudied invented Sermons of an Hour long, compoſed in the Wiſdom which this World teacheth, and ſo not profitable to Salvation, being only a profitable Livelihood to men of that Trade, who preach for Hire, and divine for Money, and ſeek for their Gain from their Quarter, and would exact and compel Money and Goods from ſuch as like not their Merchandize, if they dwell within their Quarter or Pariſh: Thoſe Prayers, Singers and Preachers for Money and Hire, are not like Chriſt's Miniſters, who received and do receive freely, and did and do freely give; and they were and are Miniſters of the manifold Grace of God. But theſe Hirelings, or Preachers for Money, have not received freely, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from God nor Man; but have purchaſed their Miniſtry with Money, and are made by Men at Schools and Colledges, and are ſent and ordained by Men, and not by the Lord, therefore they did not profit us when we were their Hearers and Diſciples; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they profit the people at all, but rather cauſe them to err, as the Falſe Prophets and Teachers did in the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s time, recorded in the 23d chapter of his Prophecy, read from the 11th verſe to the 32d verſe, and what thou findeſt teſtified againſt the Falſe Prophets in that day, is true againſt all that are found in the ſame ſpirit and practices at this day; the Prieſthood of <hi>England</hi> now (as the Prophets then) ſpeak a Viſion of their own Heart, and not out of the Mouth of the Lord; they fill peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Ears with a Noiſe of Words, and with fair Speeches or elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Diſcourſes deceive the Hearts of the Simple, talking much of the Righteous Holy Men's Words, but not living their Life; ſpeaking and ſmiting againſt Sin with that Weapon which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſtroy it in themſelves nor others; their Preaching is like that of the Scribes and Phariſees, and not as one having Authority; they ſay, <hi>Hear the Word of the Lord,</hi> but ſpeak their own words, conceivings and Inventions; they are of thoſe that ſteal the Word from their Neighbour, and boaſt in other mens Lines, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſo called, what a great Trade do theſe School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Rabbies, Doctors, Biſhops and Hireling Prieſts make of the poor, honeſt, plain Tradeſmen's Words, who were ſome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60088:16"/>Plough-men, Herds-men, Shepherds and Fiſher-men, ome of whom it's ſaid <hi>knew not a Letter?</hi> And how is this part of the World (called <hi>Europ</hi>) filled with Books and Commentaries of <hi>Papiſts, Prelates, Presbyters,</hi> and other Sects, under Pretence of opening and giving the right Meaning of their Words, whereby indeed people are divided and confuſed, and various in their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and know not well what to do, nor whom to believe, nor which to follow; ſo inſtead of gathering people into Unity, they divide and ſcatter them, and lead them into Sects and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; inſtead of Repairing the Breaches of the Walls of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> they Build up the Tower of <hi>Babylon;</hi> inſtead of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating to people the Key of Knowledge, they ſhut up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven againſt men, and neither enter themſelves, nor ſuffer thoſe that would.</p>
            <p>Theſe things we have by ſad and woful Experience known, while we were ſeeking the Living among the Dead, and wandring from Mountain to Hill, from one Prieſt and Profeſſion to another, changing, from one ſort and faſhion of Worſhip unto another, from one Sect and Opinion to another; but not from Sin to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, not from Evil to Good, nor from Death to Life; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through them all did we witneſs a Tranſlation from the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Darkneſs into the Kingdom of Chriſt, as the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did, but remained in Sin and Corruption, in Death and Darkneſs, talking of the Fame of Wiſdom, and profeſſing the holy Scriptures, the Words of holy, righteous, wiſe Men, the Words of ſanctified, juſtified and redeemed Men; but not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Life of <hi>Righteouſneſs, Wiſdom, Sanctification, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Redemption;</hi> nay, we were ſo far from it, that we did not believe it was poſſible ſo to do while on this ſide the Grave; our Teachers cauſed us to err, teaching for Doctrine the Precepts of Men, and the Thoughts and Conceivings of their own corrupt Hearts, inſtead of the Word of the Lord: ſo we were as Blind led by the Blind, and walked in Darkneſs, and in the Shadow of Death, and knew not whither we went; we ſtumbled, and knew not at what; and grouped, like blind men, for the Wall; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the divers, uncertain, fallible Voices that are in the World, which ſay, <hi>Lo, here is Chriſt; Lo, there is Chriſt;</hi> others. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60088:16"/>he is in the ſecret Chamber;</hi> and we were going forth, and wandring after them, and wearying our ſelves for a very Vanity, ſpending our Money for that which was not Bread, and our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for that which did not ſatisfie. This was our ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the day of our Ignorance, in the day of our Captivity and Bondage to the <hi>luſt of the eye, the luſt of the fleſh</hi> and <hi>the pride of life:</hi> But now we can ſay as the primitive Chriſtians did, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>We know that the Son of God is come</hi> (not only that he Did come above Sixteen Hundred Years ago, but <hi>Is come) and hath given us a good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, whereby we may know him that is true, and we are in him that's true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt; this is the true God and eternal Life:</hi> And God hath ſent the Spirit of his Son into our Hearts, whereby we can call God Father, and whereby we are led and guided out of all falſe wayes and falſe worſhips, out of the crooked wayes and by-pathes of our own finding out, into the <hi>one, true and living Way, and everlaſting Worſhip,</hi> which is <hi>in the Spirit and in the Truth,</hi> which was before all the <hi>falſe Wayes</hi> and <hi>invented Worſhips</hi> upon the Face of the Earth, and will remain when they all vaniſh away.</p>
            <p>So it is no new Sect or Opinion that we are now come unto, but the <hi>ancient Way,</hi> wherein the holy Fathers, Prophets, Apoſtles and all the Righteous walked in all Ages and Generations paſt, from <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> unto this day, which is <hi>Chriſt, the Lamb of God, that taketh away the Sin;</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt, the true Light, that lighteth every man coming into the World;</hi> who is indeed the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Saviour of his People</hi> (not in their <hi>Sins,</hi> but) <hi>from their Sins:</hi> And the true Light now ſhines out of Darkneſs in <hi>thouſands</hi> in this our Native Country, and makes manifeſt, reproves and condemns every <hi>appearance of evil,</hi> and leads the Children of it out of the ſame; this is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Way</hi> of God, wherein he is known, worſhipped and ſerved acceptably; this is his Son, in whom he is well pleaſed, and with all that are in him.</p>
            <p>Therefore in this Light muſt all the Nations that are ſaved walk; and all that walk in it witneſs Safety from, and Power and Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the Evil One, and <hi>Bleſſings, Peace</hi> and <hi>Conſolation</hi> abound in their <hi>inward man.</hi> But all that Reject and Deſpiſe, Sleight
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60088:17"/>and Contemn the <hi>Light and Grace of God teaching and ſhining with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> and the <hi>leading, guiding</hi> and <hi>moving</hi> of the Spirit of God within, they reject and deſpiſe the <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Means</hi> of <hi>Salvation,</hi> and have no Strength againſt Sin, nor Victory over their Enemy the Prince of Darkneſs, which rules within in their Hearts; but remain Slaves and Captives to him, under the <hi>Chains of darkneſs,</hi> let their Talk and Profeſſion of Chriſt and Chriſtianity be what it will, this is the Word of Truth to all our Neighbours and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whether they will hear or forbear, they ſhall find it Truein the Day of Account.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>The 17th of the 3d Moneth,</hi> 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60088:17"/>
            <head>Something after.</head>
            <p>VVHereas the Cry againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> is, <hi>That they are Diſobedient to the Law, Enemies to Magiſtrates, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, and no Friends to the Lawyers; and that they would overthrow good Government, pull down Churches, but build and repair none, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which we in ſhort ſay thus much, That this Charge is utterly without juſt Cauſe, and directly falſe: For <hi>Firſt,</hi> We are obedient to the whole Law, either <hi>actively</hi> or <hi>paſſively;</hi> and our Principle and Profeſſion leadeth us to obey every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake, <hi>not for fear of Puniſhment, but for Conſcience ſake;</hi> and herein ſtood the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Obedience in the primitive times, to every Law and Ordinance of Man that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Encouragement and Praiſe of them that did well, and to the Terror of thoſe that did Evil; to other Laws, Ordinances and Commands of Men, which did not carry this along with them, they were never actively obedient, but Witneſſers againſt them, and Sufferers by them, as might be evidenced at large by a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Examples throughout the whole Scriptures, and every Conſcientious Chriſtian Man muſt needs acknowledge, that <hi>God is to be obeyed rather then Men, when they command things repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to his Law, and impoſe upon the Mind, Heart, Conſcience and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, contrary to the Light and Law of God therein;</hi> this is to uſurp the Throne of God, and to give Laws in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which is ſpiritual, and not of this World; and where God rules &amp; governs in the hearts of men, which is and ought to be his Throne; and they know his Law
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>This is the New Covenant that God promiſed, and every</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>is to witneſs the law of God writ in his Heart, and his Fear in his Inward Parts; and none can be a</hi> Chriſtian <hi>without it.</hi>
               </note> writ therein (from whence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60088:18"/>all juſt, reaſonable, good Laws outwardly did proceed) ſuch can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tranſgreſs againſt them, nor diſobey them: So it is a manifeſt ſpirit of Envy that ſaith, <hi>We are diſobedient to Law,</hi> ſeeing our Converſation among our Neighbours throughout this Nation wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the contrary, and they find no juſt Cauſe or Occaſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, but in things appertaining to Worſhip, Church, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Conſcience, which indeed are of a ſpiritual Concern, and not belonging to Men of corrupt Minds (though they give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Name of <hi>ſpiritual men</hi>) to make and impoſe Laws about.</p>
            <p>And as concerning <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> whoſe Work is to judge between Man and Man, when they treſpaſs one againſt another, according to Equity and Righteouſneſs, without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Perſons, or any ſiniſter Intereſt; theſe we truly Love and Honour, who bear not the Sword in vain, but relieve the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and judge the Cauſe of the Innocent, and help the Poor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Mighty,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6, 7, 8.</note> and are a Terror to the Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers; theſe judge for God, and not for Men; and the Lord is with them in Judgment, and the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and Preſence of the Lord will be upon them.</p>
            <p>Now, it is the Evil-doers that are Enemies to Magiſtracy, and that make and create Trouble to good Magiſtrates, ſuch as break and violate the Law of God and Man, and kill and ſteal, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery, and bear falſe witneſs againſt them, and covet their Neighbours Wife, Ox, Aſs, nor any thing that is his, &amp;c. theſe are they that are Haters of Law and Magiſtrates, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to Authority.</p>
            <p>Now we are kept by the Grace of God out of theſe things, and do by vertue of the Nature and Power thereof the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law, which ſhews the Effect of the Law written in our Hearts; and ſo becauſe we love and obey the Law and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, we fulfil the End of them both: But they that ſay, They love and honour the Law and Magiſtracy, and yet are found in the Evil-doing, they lye, and do not the Truth, and would ſubvert the Law, and overthrow Magiſtracy, and all Good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment among men, and are direct Enemies to Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>Now, to thoſe that ſay, we <hi>Hate thoſe that are Miniſters of the Goſpel;</hi> we ſay, and that truly, that it is a Falſe Accuſation;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60088:18"/>for we love no men more: they are indeed Embaſſadours of Peace and Reconcilation of Mankind to God; and they have the Power of Perſwaſion, and in the Spirit of Love and Meekneſs do prevail, and turn many from the Evil of their Wayes, and direct them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Good Old Way and Ancient Path of Peace, which the Righteous in all Ages walked in, from <hi>Enoch</hi> unto this day; <hi>in which Way the Wayfaring man; though a Fool, cannot err</hi> [mark that] and ſeek and enquire for this Way.</p>
            <p>Now, all ſuch as pretend to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, and do not do and Effect this Work in and among people, it's an evident ſign the Lord never ſent them, and that they are not in Deed what they profeſs in Words; yet let all know, that we hate no men's Perſons, though we bear witneſs againſt Deceit and Hypocritical Pretences amongſt men of all Degrees and Profeſſions, and would have men to be and to be known to be as they are in the ſight of God, where all Coverings avail not.</p>
            <p>And to ſuch as ſay, we <hi>are no Friends to the Lawyers;</hi> and that, we <hi>would overthrow good Government,</hi> &amp;c. We ſay, we are Friends to all men; and ſhould rejoyce to ſee good Government ſet up among them; and eſpecially amongſt the Lawyers, that, that common Honeſty and Right might be fulfilled among them, as is among other Trades-men, who ſell a Penny-worth for a Penny: And we deſire the Law might be declared in ſuch plain terms, that the Lawyer Knowledge and Counſel might be certain; that he might undertake to do Peoples work and buſineſs to their Content, if he expect to receive their Money; as other Trades-men muſt: And that they would be ſo honeſt, that when People come to them with a bad Cauſe (which the Law is againſt) that they would Inſtruct and Adviſe them better, and refuſe to appear in it for love of Money: Then would Equity enter, and Juſtice run down as a mighty Stream. But when Lawyers undertake bad Cauſes, for bad People, for love of Money; Equity is obſtructed, and the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Juſtice ſtopped, delayed, deferred, if not pervented, and turned backward; and by this means, honeſt men are unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vexed, troubled and abuſed, trhough the Promiſciouſneſs of the Law, and the crafty skill, Rhetorick and Intereſt of a bad Lawyer, and by theſe a poor man's Cauſe, though never ſo good,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60088:19"/>is overthrown; all theſe things we would have amended; and have every man honeſt in his Imployment, and do as he would be done by; and this only being obſerved, will bring People to be good friends, and love one another, and live together in Peace, as becometh Chriſtians: And then we believe the Lawyers would not have ſo great a trade and Imployment. But if we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no friends to the Lawyers, becauſe we deſire them to be honeſt; if that be a fault, we muſt and ſhall be found guilty; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are ready to judge and conclude, that the Deceit, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſelf-Intereſt, and love of Money among the Lawyers and thoſe divers Officers exerciſed about the Law, is a ſore Evil, and a great burthen to this Nation: <hi>And that when Judges are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored as at firſt, and Councellors as at the beginning,</hi> ſuch Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be ſwept away, and ſuch abuſes will be reformed, and good Government will be eſtabliſhed; firſt within in the Minds and Hearts of men, and then without, which is our hearty deſire to ſee effected in this our Native Country.</p>
            <p>And as for the cry againſt us, that we would pull down Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We are ſo far from it, that we wiſh, where there is one Church of Chriſt in a Nation, that there were an hundred: But as for old Maſs-houſes and ſuch like, which are now uſed as Shops for thoſe that make a trade of Preaching, to ſell their Common-Prayer and Studied Sermons in, which ignorant Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple call Churches, thoſe that believe them to be ſo, and love and delight in them, and thoſe that drive a profitable Trade therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is moſt right and proper forſuch to repair and build them; and ſuch have a Propriety therein. So not lawful nor right, that we or any ſhould pull down, impair or demolliſh any man's propriety; being alſo directly contrary to the Fundamental Law of this the Land of our Nativity, which all ought to obſerve and obey.</p>
            <p>Now a Church of Chriſt, according to the Teſtimony of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures,
<note place="margin">What a Church of Chriſt is.</note> is a Company of Believers in Chriſt, who areledand guided by his Spirit, learn of him, keep his Sayings, obſerve his Doctrine, and walk according to his Precepts and Commandments; and this Church may meet together in a Houſe, as they did in the primitive Times; but a Houſe cannot be a Church: and though the Church
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60088:19"/>of Chriſt be one, yet there may be many of theſe Churches in divers Places, Nations and Countries, as there was in the primitive Times divers Churches in <hi>Aſia, Corinth, Galatia,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> laſt Chap.</note> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> writes a Salutation to <hi>Pricil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> and <hi>Aquilla,</hi> and the Church in their Houſe; but never called a Houſe a Church.</p>
            <p>And the Church of Chriſt needs no man to build or repair it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all living Stones, fitly joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together by him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note that the Word</hi> Church <hi>throughout the New Teſtament ought to be rendred</hi> Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>as in ancient Tranſlations and primitive Times, and hath no relation to a</hi> Houſe, <hi>as peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple falſly imagine and eſteem.</hi>
               </note> who is the Maſter-builder, Foundation and chief Corner-ſtone alſo; and this Church edifies it ſelf in Love, and grows up an holy Habitation for God in the Spirit; and this is the Subſtance and Anti-type of that Tabernacle and outward Temple which God once commanded to be built, and was the Glory of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in its time, and the only Place wherein God appeared and was worſhipped; but now he dwells not in Temples made with Hands, neither is worſhipped with men's Hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he giveth to all Life and Breath, and all things, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.25.</p>
            <p>Now, it is a very fooliſh, ridiculous and wicked thing for thoſe called Chriſtians to take their Neighbours and Country men by the Throat, and ſay to them, <hi>Give us Money to build and repair our Church, or we will Excommunicate you, and throw your Bodies into Goal, where they ſhall rot, and ſpoil and ruin your Trades and Families, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you have any Precept, Preſident or Example for ſuch kind of work in the holy Scriptures (which you pretend to be your Rule for Faith and Practice) let's know the Chapter and Verſe where it is written, or elſe be aſhamed and Repent of your Work, and make not Chriſtianity (by your Wicked Practices) a Stink in the Noſtrils of Atheiſts and Unbelievers.</p>
            <p>So, whoever thou art that readſt theſe things, thou mayſt in ſhort underſtand, that we are cryed out againſt in this Age, and reported and preſented to be ſuch like Monſters as <hi>Paul</hi> (that harmleſs man)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60088:20"/>was ſaid to be, when he was called <hi>a Peſtilent Fellow, a Ring-Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Sects, a Turner of the World up-ſide down, not fit to live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> and this cry aroſe chiefly from the Prieſts, Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, Doctors, and great Profeſſors of thoſe times, which ſoon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced the common People, and it ariſeth from the ſame ſpirit and like perſons now againſt us, and for no other Cauſe then bearing witneſs to the Truth. Therefore we would have all people take heed how they hear and receive Reports, leſt they judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Innocent without fair Tryal,</hi> and hedge up their own way, and abide in the midſt of Darkneſs; but be ready to obey that good Advice and Exhortation, <hi>Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good:</hi> And as they come to find and hold faſt that which is good, it will quickly furniſh them with Strength againſt that which is Evil, and make them free from it alſo, and deliver them from thoſe Chains and Fetters of carnal private Opinions traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and ſuperſtitiouſly introduced into their Minds and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, through the Wiles of the Enemy, Deceit and crafty Devices of Men of corrupt Minds, who make a Trade of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Scriptures, and ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own Bellies; who though they may have a Zeal for their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, it's not according to Knowledge, as is demonſtrated by their Fruits, who like <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was a Phariſee, in his Blind Zeal thought he did well in Perſecuting the Church of Chriſt, and in haling the Saints to Priſon by Vertue of his Orders and Packet of Letters from the Prieſts; however, he did it ignorantly, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obtained Mercy. If Dr. <hi>Parr</hi> and the reſt of our Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have thrown us into Goal in a Blind Zeal for their Religion, and Excommunicated us out of their Church becauſe they believe us to be more <hi>wicked, prophane</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> then others that dwell within the Pariſh, we ſay, if it be ſo, their Sin is the leſs: but if it be upon the account of <hi>Self-Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> (as is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) their Sin will be marked as with the Point of a Diamond, and it will be much if they find a Place of Repentance: let thoſe concerned conſider of it, before it be too late; for you muſt be accountable to God (if not to Men alſo) for your Actions; and let it not ſeem a light thing in your Eyes, to throw Perſons into Goal, from their Wives, Families, Trades and Imployments, for a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60088:20"/>thing of nought, only call it <hi>Contempt</hi> to your <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when in time, it may yet appear, that we attending your Courts from time to time, and offering our Anſwers under our Hands and Seals by Proxy, was ſufficient to prevent you of that fained pretence of <hi>Contempt,</hi> upon which you have unlawfully by your lying Lips Suplicated, Prayed, &amp; gained a <hi>Writ</hi> againſt us, out of the King's <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery,</hi> but were never willing to let us have a fair Tryal, neither in your cruel Spiritual Court, nor at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law; uſing Deceit and Lyes, as hath been hinted before to hinder us of a <hi>prohibition.</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> The Law of <hi>England</hi> is very tender of the Liberties, Lives and Eſtates of Men, and when Juſtice takes place, ſome may be called to Account for their heady, raſh, unlawful arbitrary Proceedings.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing you know, or may know, that the Law is not on your ſides, in your thus dealing with us, how is it that you are ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and overgrown with Envy, as to give the Jaylor ſo ſtrict a Charge concerning us, <hi>That he muſt keep us cloſe Priſoners, as if we were great Malefactors?</hi> would it not pleaſe you well, if his Heart was as cruel towards us as yours, and that he would exerciſe as much Hardneſs of Heart, unlawful and unchriſtian Practices upon us in Priſon, as you have done to bring us thither? It's hardly a Queſtion whether ſome of you would not be glad if he would throng us together into ſome ſtinking Dungeon, where we might ſoon end our Dayes, and not live to ſee you mend, nor be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to your works.</p>
            <p>But God be thanked, he hath ſo ordered and prepared the Minds and Hearts of many Jaylors in <hi>England,</hi> that they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſhew, and manifeſt Humanity, Favour and Kindneſs towards us, who ſuffer for Conſcience-ſake, and not for Evil doing.</p>
            <p>It's ſaid, (<hi>Luke</hi> 10.33.) the <hi>Samaritan</hi> was more compaſſionate, or mercifull then the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and the <hi>Levite,</hi> and that, <hi>Publicans and Harlots go into the Kingdom of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.31.</note> before the chief Prieſts and Elders of the people;</hi> this Chriſt ſaid many Ages ago to the Prieſt and Elders then; and it is infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly true in this Age, for the Hireling Prieſt who Perſecutes for his Belly, and the Elders of the People, who are Cruel and Violent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60088:21"/>againſt their Neighbours about Church and Worſhip;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.46.</note> and the <hi>Lawyers who lay heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens upon the People; theſe ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men</hi> (now as then) <hi>and neither enter themſelves, nor ſuffer thoſe that would.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is from theſe ſort of Men that profeſs Law and Religion,
<note place="margin">☞</note> but practice neither, that Threatnings and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints have been, and are made againſt ſome Jaylors, for beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves kindly towards us, their honeſt Priſoners, who they can truſt to go forth and buy themſelves Bread and ſmall Bear, and other neceſſaries at the beſt hand, knowing they will return again, according to their word. But the Envy of our Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, now they have thrown us in Priſon from our Imployments, (being moſt poor Trades-men, and have but little Money) would by threats and other means, ingage the Jaylor to abridge us of that Liberty, or of any kindneſs he is capable to ſhew unto us: If this be the Fruits of your Religion, and Spiritual-Courted men, and the effect of <hi>D. P's</hi> teaching and Doctrine among you this many Years, you will by this never win us to be of your Church, nor to be in love with your Way nor Works. To conclude, we may ſay of you, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of his two Sons, <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, You are Brethren; Inſtruments of Cruelty are in your Habitations. Oh my Soul, come not thou into their ſecret, unto their Aſſembly, &amp;c. Gen.</hi> 49.5.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Rawbone, Henry Day.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 29. line 14. for <hi>Law</hi> read <hi>Love.</hi> p. 34. l. 23. for them r. their Neighbour l. 24. for nor r. or. p. 35. l. 33. for pervented r. perverted. l. 35. for <hi>trhough</hi> r. <hi>through.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60088:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
